Software engineers have power at this
company.
>> This is Adrian. He grew from a new grad
to a principal engineer at Meta and
shared the story of how his career grew.
>> So the first thing I did was like, "Hey
manager, I'm not going to do what my job
is and what the team is doing because I
think there's an opportunity there.
>> What's your biggest learning from the
principal engineer promotion?"
>> You need to have like the impact in the
underlying work, but then it is also way
easier to like build the consensus ahead
of time. The advice he gave could help
any tech career. How do you maximize
your luck when it comes to people
opportunity?
>> Oh, so many thoughts. Uh the first one
is, you know, like I
>> Here's his full career story.
>> Can you tell me a little bit about the
first team that you joined and why you
picked it?
>> So, I was actually pre-allocated. Uh I
joined what was then called the data
science team. Uh which you and I have
talked about a little is a little
confusing. uh because what we call data
scientists nowadays is very different
from what was data science then. In
early 2011
12 there was this emergence of big data
uh and you know mainly at LinkedIn and
Facebook teams of statisticians and
computer scientists and early machine
learning uh researchers leveraging a lot
of data to build better products. So
that was like the very early days of
doing AB testing and doing AB testing at
SCA at scale uh doing measurement and
proper measurement of things and so that
was that team I was pre-allocated to
that team because you know I had a PhD I
was working on social network analysis
uh I so I was joining this like small
team of like 20 or so people uh for the
people who know the Facebook stack you
know that team had be had been behind
like the whole AB testing platform for
the
had been behind a lot of like all of the
data pipelines that are being used to
measure and count everything. Uh we
would often joke that you know at the
end of the day we were just doing big
counting. Uh and so I was pre-allocated
to the data science team.
>> Did you see yourself more as a data
scientist at the time or a software
engineer?
>> You know, it's very funny. I have this
very distinct memory of a conversation,
my first one-on-one I had with my
manager, Cameron Marlo, who was managing
the data science team at the time. Uh,
we were standing in line uh about to
have lunch and I was kind of I don't
know, I was kind of a little
pretentious. I was like, you know, I
have a PhD. I'm not like I'm not a
software engineer. And he was like, hey,
software engineers have power at this
company. You are a software engineer.
Don't pigeon hole yourself into like a
category or an area that is not like the
most important job at the company. You
are a software engineer. Software
engineers create the products obviously
in partnership with PMs and designers
and all that but software engineering
carries a lot of weight and and yeah
since then like I've always considered
myself a a software engineer like that
is my primary job. My title has always
been software engineer or you know my
official workday title. Uh I think I was
like a research scientist for a while uh
in like the outwardly displayed things.
Uh I was a data scientist for a while
but no always a software engineer. And
then like I mentioned to you around 2014
or so the role of product analytics got
renamed to data scientists across the
company. So all of a sudden we moved
from having you know 20 data scientists
or 30 data scientists all with PhDs
doing data analysis doing software
engineering and stats to having you know
500 or so data scientists doing mostly
product analytics. Uh which was kind of
like a crisis in identity in the team I
was on at the time. Uh but you know we
quickly moved on like at the end of the
day the title was not the important
part. The important part was the impact
of the work we were doing. Can you
explain the difference between the
product analytics and the old data
science function? I'm curious what what
are things that an old data scientist
would do that a data scientist today
would not be expected to do.
>> Well, one that was like when we were
building uh you know deltoid and like
all of those AB testing tools. Uh
nowadays data scientists would like are
mostly users of those of those tools.
they're not the one who have like
defined the algorithm or the sampling
strategy or the double bootstrap or the
sorry the bootstrapping that you're
using to like compare test groups and
whatnot. Uh so it was a lot of like you
know people like Dean Eckles and Eton
Bachi uh like really amazing
statisticians who were like building
those tools that are now powering the
company. So they were the tool builders
more than the tool users.
>> And those tools allowed the data science
function to to scale. That people
without that deep statistical
understanding could go into a tool and
understand data much more easily than
someone in the past. Yeah. There was
just another example of the stuff we did
at the time. Uh I worked on how rumors
spread on social network. That was like
my very first project at the company. uh
I worked with uh amazing researchers
Lada Adamic like she was eventually my
manager and a director of data science
at the company. Uh but her background
was like as an academic doing research
on social networks. Uh and so with her
and Alex Dao and a few others uh we
spent the first six months I was at the
company analyzing how rumors spread on
social network. Now, by rumors, I really
want to be specific here. Like, I'm not
talking about fake news, uh, which is a
slightly different flavor. I'm talking
about rumors, mostly memes, uh, and you
know, the type of stuff that end up on,
say, snopes. Uh, and the stuff we were
looking at was the shape of those
cascades, how do they spread? Do they
tend to like, you know, spread mostly in
long chains? Do they tend to fan out?
Uh, and it's really dependent on a few
things. Uh, and there were like
fascinating results. We found we found
that like false rumors have a tendency
to spread faster than true rumors and
even if you point out that a rumor is
false that doesn't really limited
spread. So that was the type of work we
were doing. Uh and you know like I spent
about six eight months doing that uh
published maybe two or three papers. I
think the impact we had on the company
was affecting the weight of re-shares in
newsfeed. Uh we were like, "Hey, if we
continue doing like too many re-shares,
we're going to lose organic content." Uh
but that was the impact. So, you know,
my manager at the time was like, you
know, you wrote three papers uh help
tweak newsfeed meets all go figure out
something impactful for the company.
It's super interesting the false rumors
spreading faster than true ones. And I
mean, it matches intuition. If
something's wrong, people are more
likely to then reshare because they say
this is wrong, which then some
percentage of people who agree with it
will share it because it's right.
Another polarizing set of people will
share it again and say this is wrong. I
I think it's more that false rumors tend
to be more egregious and because they're
more egregious, they are inherently more
sharable or more viral. uh like true
things tend to be more boring than false
things on average.
>> I I want to go into your your first
promotion story kind of getting to the
senior engineering level. Can you talk
about the story behind doing that at
Instagram?
>> Yeah. So, you know, after letting this
rumor work, uh I was very lucky to just
meet Mike Kger, who was, you know,
co-founder and CTO at Instagram. Uh
Instagram had been acquired in September
of 2012. It was a very small team at the
time. I started talking to them in like
early 2013ish
and the team was still relatively small.
Like the core Instagram team at the time
was probably 30 people and then there
were like a lot of like Facebook people
around helping uh on the safety side. Uh
there were a few people starting to help
on the data side. Uh just to give an
idea of like the maturity of the time.
This is when the very first data
pipelines to count how many users on
Instagram uh were were created and I was
like hey this is like a cool product uh
you know this little photo social
network that we've acquired uh they
don't really do anything with data uh
there's no personalization there's an
opportunity to do something cool here
and so the first thing I started helping
with was the explore tab the explore tab
you know circa 2012 2013 was basically
the most popular content on Instagram
and with a few others, we decided to add
a little bit of personalization to that
and surface, you know, popular content
from your friend, content you might be
interested in. And so we did that. We
started building, you know, like a bunch
of like different sources. And and then
there was this question of like, well,
how do we know if it's good or not? Now,
obviously, it's probably going to be
better than only having popular content
on the platform, but there was a desire
to like understand the impact of what
we're doing. And similarly, I was also
like helping out with some people
looking at growth and user acquisition.
And you're like, can we plug into
Facebook and like deep link you into
Instagram or like promote Instagram
within Facebook? How do we measure
conversions here? Instagram didn't have
any AB testing system. So, you know, as
an old IC4, I was like, you know what? I
think Instagram needs AB testing. So I
talked to like a few PMs and I talked to
Kger and Kevin Cyester and everyone was
like hey yeah you know we have like
bigger fish to fry right now. Uh
Instagram was in the midst of in what
we're calling integration which was
migrating Instagram from AWS where it
was running to the Facebook infra uh for
cost and all of that. And so they were
like, "Yeah, you know, like your little
AB testing idea is good. We'll come to
that later, but like we have like really
important things we need to do now. Uh
so please don't bug us." I was like, "I
don't know. Let me try and see if I can
build that." Uh and so I roped a PM uh
Jeff Caner uh to get, you know, air
cover on what I was doing and I just
kind of hacked something together. Now,
Facebook had an AB testing system. So, I
was like, I want to reuse this as much
as possible. But like I said, Instagram
was running in a different
infrastructure. So, how how can you plug
those things and connect them together?
Uh, I did the dumbest hackiest, probably
very expensive thing I could do, which
was add a custom Facebook API endpoint
that was allowed listed on the Instagram
app ID, which was essentially log those
things. And so, that way you could like
log all exposures over the internet,
sending that from AWS using the Facebook
API. Uh, now you're logging your
exposures. So that's like half of the
problem is solved. The other half is
like how do you hash users into the
right groups? That was like, you know,
50 100 lines of code. So replicated that
on the Instagram side. And at that
point, I just had a system to hash users
into buckets, log exposures, and we
already had some like data in our uh
data warehouse. So, I could connect that
to the backend delta of our AB testing
system. So, I had all the different
pieces. So, at that point, I was like,
okay, I can kind of like run some like
web experiments. Uh, unfortunately, we
don't have a website or it was like very
early days of the Instagram website. So
I think the first thing I did was like a
a serverside AA test to prove that it
worked. And then I found like a mobile
engineer uh who was willing to you know
help me with like the iOS code and with
the Android code and then we started
running like one two small experiments
like very small things just to prove
that like the system worked and that it
was scaling and it did. Uh so that's the
story of like how we brought AB testing
to Instagram. Uh now obviously after
integration all that all everything has
been like probably written four or five
times since then but that was the story
behind my promotion. I built that thing.
By the way I had no idea the promotions
existed at that point. You know I was
like a a little IC4 who was completely
naive is just working on things because
I was excited about them. I didn't pick
that because I thought it would be
successful. I picked that because I
needed it for this other thing I wanted
to build. you know, come PSC season at
the end of the year, my manager was
like, "Congratulations, we're promoting
you to IC5." I'm like, "What does that
even mean? What is an IC5?" Uh, yeah.
And then I transitioned that AB testing
system to this newly created
datagramgram team, uh, which went on to
own and maintain that.
>> Interesting. I I can already tell in
your early career story there are
examples of unusual agency in chasing
things down. I mean, sounds like no one
told you to build this. And you have a
few examples in that story of you went
up to random people like the CTO of
Instagram, you went up to a mobile
engineer, you said, "Hey, can you you
want to join in on this this
initiative?" It sounds like that's
pretty standout that you had that
behavior so early in your career.
>> I never really thought about that this
way. It was just I think the early days
of Facebook were very, very bottoms up.
Everyone kind of operated like that or
at least that's how I understood the
world right you need to do something and
you can't do it yourself so you try and
find someone to help you with it you
know the early days of Facebook I mean
obviously we still have hackathons
nowadays but there was such a big
hackathon culture in the first six
months I think I probably did six
hackathons once a month every like on a
Thursday evening you would spend the
entire night in the office with other
people hacking on
that was not related to your day job.
And that that to me was the culture of
Facebook. Uh and so naturally when it
came to my day job, it's like of course
I'm going to hack on something. Of
course I'm going to try and figure out
how do I achieve the thing I want to
achieve.
>> Were there cultural differences between
the early Instagram team and Facebook at
the time?
>> So I never officially joined the
Instagram team. So on the data science
team, we were kind of operating as
consultants helping different teams
around the company. Uh and so you know
we would do like six month two-year
stints embedded in a team but my
reporting chain never changed. Uh I was
very lucky to have few managers. I know
that like a lot of folks have changed
managers like every six months. Uh I
think in my first two three years at the
company I had two managers uh despite
working on very different teams. Not
joining Instagram, by the way,
officially uh is probably one of the
biggest mistake I've made in my career.
Not to say I have any regrets. Uh this
is more the flavor of like I didn't buy
a bunch of Bitcoin in 2013 type of
regret. Uh but I think my career would
have been very different if I decided to
join instead of like move on to
something else. In terms of culture,
Instagram was like it really felt like a
very small startup within a startup. you
know, Facebook was like 2,000ish
employees. Instagram, like the whole
core team, everyone working on
Instagram, uh, we all fit in one big
conference room. It was like 30, 40
people. And there was such a big focus
on design and craft over data that was
very different. But other than that, it
was to me like that same like energy of
like just creating stuff. When you say
it was the biggest mistake that you've
ever made in your career, what do you
mean by that? And where do you think
your career would have been if you
joined Instagram?
>> That is really hard to tell. I I think
my career growth would have been
accelerated. I might have like reached
certain levels faster if I had joined
that team at the time. Uh you know, if I
look at the folks who were working with
me in that space at that time, uh they
went on to have really fantastic
careers. uh and you know hitting like
IC7s, IC 8s, IC9s, IC10s way sooner than
I have uh or probably ever will. Like I
said, it's really hard to know what the
counterfactual is. Uh and I'm also very
happy with where I'm at in my career.
It's just this is like a road not taken.
You know, after that, I understand that
you built some some frameworks and you
worked on some additional tooling that
was highly leveraged at the company. Can
you talk about the story behind your IC7
or senior staff promo?
>> So, like I said, you know, I was kind of
like playing around uh like all those
different projects bringing data to like
non-data uh teams and I had my hits and
then in other cases it didn't really pan
out. So, I got roped into this project
to count the number of people using one
of Facebook's property. I'm not going to
spend a lot of time talking about it,
but in the process of doing that, that
was around 2015 or so, we had to do a
bunch of data processing. We had to do a
bunch of machine learning uh and
inference. And the tools we had were
just icky. They didn't really work well.
Like the developer experience was
horrible. Uh we would have to like, you
know, work within like one data
pipelining framework and then move to
like another thing to do the machine
learning and the inference and then go
back and forth. And I was like, "This is
this is not fun. I'm like wasting so
much time just going back and forth."
Uh, and so I started building this
little library that essentially let you
do data pipelining within the machine
learning orchestration framework. And at
first that was just like me writing a
bunch of helper scripts for myself cuz I
didn't want to have to go back and
forth. I didn't want to have to like
deal with landing code in two different
code bases and like synchronizing all of
that. I was like, I want my code to live
in one thing and do all of my thing in
this codebase and then I'll be happy.
But in the process of doing that, I just
started tinkering a little and I was
like, why is that whenever I need to
write a data pipeline, I have to like
write the same boiler plate over and
over again? It's always the same thing.
Why can't I set those things to be the
defaults? And so, you know, I kind of
like whittleled away a lot of the boiler
plate that you had to write. And so I
put together this library where if you
were building a data pipeline in the
machine learning orchestration framework
FB learner flow what would take you say
300 lines of code in like the canonical
data pipelining system would probably
take you 20 lines of code. You had this
escape hatch to like add all the
configuration but by default it did the
right thing. And at that point I was
hooked. I was like I am building a thing
that can make people's lives easier.
forget about this like counting number
of people on Facebook. Other people are
going to figure that out. I want to help
those people move faster. And so then I
started looking at like other things
where people were wasting time. And at
the time if you were a data scientist
like as a product analyst uh if you were
a machine learning engineer the way you
worked was by building or setting up
your own tools. Half of the company was
using Jupiter for notebooks. The other
half of the company was using R Studio,
uh, which uses this like statistical
program language R. And the way you
would set that up is you you would look
at one of like 10 different wiks that
were all outdated, and you would have to
like set that up either on a desk server
or on your machine. A lot of manual
steps. And I was like, that's kind of
silly. Uh, we should just make it so
everyone has a Jupiter instance running
if they want and they don't have to
configure it. And so I just kind of like
started building that. I remember
telling my manager, you know, it was
probably February. I was like, "Hey,
this is the beginning of the half. I'm
going to take two, three months to just
hack on this, uh, and if it doesn't pan
out come, you know, April, I'll just
find another project to like save the
half and like, you know, not get the
need most." And so I started hacking on
this, roped in a couple more people, uh,
and we built what eventually became the
very first version of Bento, which is
the Noble platform based on Jupiter
that's used all across the company. And
at first, Bento was really, really dumb.
It was just a script that would set up
Jupiter for you. But we had this vision
behind it. What if instead of just being
this like external tool that you have to
set up that doesn't communicate with
anything at the company, we integrated
that better within the rest of the
tooling. What if you could just open a
browser, type Bento, and now you have a
notebook that's running and you already
have the libraries that are built within
the company that you can reuse instead
of having to like figure out how to do
that manually. What if you could have
like other programming languages? uh
eventually you know people will start
hacking hack into that and so over the
course of about a year or so uh we
started like putting the system
together. A big thing that I worked on
after that was building Bento on demand
where instead of having a dev server
where we would set up the system for you
you could just request an ondemand
instance you could work on that and then
release it. uh because we're doing that
for like development environment and
we're like yeah that makes a lot of
sense you don't have to maintain a dev
server and so in the process of doing
that I you know I helped lead the
development of the platform uh but more
importantly I put the team together uh I
transitioned into a tech lead manager
role uh started building a team uh and
the way I built the team was hiring
people who were very excited about the
tooling world actually I just hired a
bunch of people who were already
building tooling on the side in their
spare time. I was like, "Hey, do you
want this to be your full-time job?
Sounds like you like to do this thing.
It's super impactful. Do you want to do
this full time?" Uh, and so, you know, I
brought in like a bunch of like amazing
people. Uh, so good team like six,
seven, eight people. Uh, and so I got
promoted to, uh, TLM2 mostly on my IC
work. Uh, and the vision I had for
Bento. And TLM2 for people who are
outside the company is equivalent to
senior manager which is equivalent to
senior staff engineer um in the
industry. And when you hear these great
stories of new infrastructure or tooling
that everyone takes for granted today,
what I want to know is what is the
stepbystep process on how you actually
get the tooling from an idea to
something that everyone is using. So for
Bento the notebook platform uh the
answer is we didn't really try to get
adoption within people's existing
workflows. What I did was twofold. One
we targeted boot camp in data camp. So
boot camp and data camp for non-fasers
is where you the thing you go through
when you onboard at the company. and we
just went to data camp and we told
everyone who was working with data, this
is the way you set up your developer
environment. You just use this thing or
you can also just like go do it manually
if you want. Uh but you can also just
like type this one word and you have
your developer environment. The company
was growing like crazy at the time,
right? And so when you have this like
amount of insane growth and you know the
company is going to say like double in
size within like a year or two you you
get your growth from like all of those
newcomers who don't know the legacy
systems and then you get the stragglers
because everyone else around them then
use the new system. So that was like a
lot of the growth strategy behind Bento.
The other thing we did with Bento was
provide support and maintenance for the
legacy systems. Uh and so you know we
built trust with users that way. So if
you were installing Jupiter by yourself,
you could go to that group that was
unmonitored before us and we provide
help and we provide support. Uh and then
over time, you know, after building that
trust, we would start encouraging people
and be like, yeah, you know, this like
thing you want to do, I can give you a
recipe that's going to take 25 steps to
do that or we've actually built that in
bento. It doesn't really change your
workflow. It'll just make your life
easier. uh you'll move to that. So to
summarize, you know, step one, find an
easy way of getting a bunch of users
because network effects work. Step two,
for the people who are on the legacy
systems, just provide value to them.
That's super interesting because when I
think of these developer offerings, I
just always assume that you're going to
have to influence a group of people that
is using something today to switch off
of something. in this particular case in
a growing company there's this whole new
user base is like all these people
coming in they're they're deciding from
a fresh slate and it sounds like your
offering was a superior product in a
sense so it was a pretty easy sell and
then the other thing we did too was go
to you know Alex Schulz who's now the
CMO of the company but I was head of
analytics at the time and Brady Brady
Laach uh and we just told them hey we
know that there's a lot of pain within
your teams, we want to help. We think
that this is the first step. And you
know, I remember Brady saying, "Yeah,
this is this is a good first step.
There's like those like 20 other things
you need to go fix." I was like, "Okay,
let's take it one step at a time. Uh,
and let's let's start talking more."
There was no team at the time really
building tools for data science and
machine learning. Uh and so this is when
I actually ended up leaving the core
data science team and I reorked myself
into the dev info organization to start
that team really focused on data
developer tools. At the beginning of
this story you mentioned you took on
some performance system risk. you you
literally told your manager, "Hey, I'm
gonna take on and build something that
has a lot of potential, but also it
might flop entirely and then we can
scramble to figure out performance so
that you know, you don't get a below um
meets all rating." I'm curious cuz at
that time the the industry was not as
intense when it comes to turnurning out
short-term results. Do you think that
trying to do something like that today
would be more difficult? Do you have any
advice on more generally how to take on
risk to pursue these higher rewards?
>> I think the consequences of
underperforming now are more drastic
than they were 10 years ago. For sure. I
think the strategies when you want to
take risk is the same. Make sure you're
on the same page with your hierarchy and
your manager. Uh at the end of the day,
like you know, we are all evaluated
based on our expectations. If you're not
aligned on what is expected of you with
your manager, then that is a problem.
Now, you know, I was on a team whose job
was to provide help with data. I was
data consultant in a way, right? Now,
the thing I was building was tooling and
infrastructure, not at all data
consulting. So, the first thing I did
was like, hey manager, I'm not going to
do what my job is and what the team is
doing because I think there's an
opportunity there. Are you okay with me
doing this? Can we make it so, you know,
we carve out two, three months for me to
go explore that and make that part of my
expectation? If it pans out, great. If
it doesn't pan out, well, I was expected
to go explore this. It was a calculated
risk. We all agreed as a team, my
manager, my skip, myself that like that
was a thing I was going to do. And at
that point, you know, there's an
agreement. This is the job you're going
to do. Everyone is on the same page. Uh,
I think it is a lot riskier to go and do
your own thing. You know, you you lock
yourself in a room, do your thing for 3
months, show up, and you're like, I did
this thing and then everyone's like,
"Yeah, but no one knew you were doing
this thing." Overcommunicate, I think,
is really the strategy I would
recommend. And also be ready to hear no.
Like I was very lucky to have a manager
that said, "Yeah, you know, I think that
makes it's risky, but it makes sense. Go
do that." Uh I've had you know instances
later on in my career where I wanted to
go do a thing and I tried building that
consensus and what I told was no don't
do that. You mentioned that you
transitioned to a TLM during this leg of
your career as well. What was the
thinking behind that transition?
>> I was building the team right you know
we were building this product. I knew we
had to scale and we needed more people.
And so then the question was like, do I
go hire someone to manage me and the
rest of the team, someone who might come
in with like a different vision for the
team or a different strategy uh or do I
try this management thing? And so to me
it was really driven by a desire to like
just you know take this little crew we
had assembled and like lead them or
support them uh in building this product
we wanted to build. Uh so it was kind of
like a natural like evolution. It was
not really a thought out I want to be a
manager. I'm going to transition into
management and find a role like that. It
was just I was tech leading that team.
We needed more people. The team needed a
manager. I ended up being the manager.
>> So after you got this IC7 promotion, I
understand that you left Meta with
desire to start your own company.
>> Yes.
>> What was the thinking there and the
story behind you leaving? How did that
go?
>> At that point, I had been at the company
for about seven years. That was the only
company I had ever worked at. You know,
my professional experience before that
was like I said, doing a PhD, working in
my own corner. Seven years of Facebook
uh and growing tremendously, learning a
lot, but also not really knowing what
happened in the outside world. Uh and
then I think there was also maybe a
little bit of hubris. I was like, I
built this like platform that's being
used by at that point 60% of all people
doing data at the company. Uh I was
like, I can go build that externally.
you know, if Facebook needed this in
2018, the world is going to need that in
like 2020 and I'm going to go build it.
So, I left and I thought I was going to
do a startup and then I realized that
I'm not an entrepreneur or I wasn't at
the time. You know, might change in the
future, but at the time that was not who
I was. I really enjoyed going deep into
technical problems and I think I had
maybe underestimated the amount of work
at the time needed for me to like build
or rebuild by myself what like you know
our team of like six had spent two years
building on like a very mature
infrastructure. I often joke that like I
left the company to do a startup and I
ended up taking a sbatical instead. Uh
it was wonderful to travel the world. I
went to like a lot of like wonderful
places but I did not start a startup. I
built a few prototypes. uh you know I
found other people to work with with
whom we had like different ideas uh
nothing really crystallized. What were
the the skill gaps between yourself at
the time a successful tech lead and an
entrepreneur?
>> In order to be a successful entrepreneur
you need to be able to delegate the hard
stuff, right? You scale yourself through
others. And to me at that point it
basically meant that whenever something
became interesting I would have to find
someone else to do it. My involvement
would have to be superficial. Uh and so
you know I could hack a prototype
together but like if I wanted to take it
to the next step I would probably need
to find like some engineers to go work
on that while I go like you know try and
figure out how to get people to use the
thing in the first place. And I wasn't
really into that. So after the sbatical,
you boomerang back to Meta. What was
your thinking behind going to Meta?
>> So like I said, CO happened. I was
living in New York at the time. Uh and I
was stuck in my tiny apartment. Uh and I
don't know, on a whim, I decided to buy
a house in Denver. Uh so moved to
Denver, bought the house, got a
mortgage, and I was like, I need like a
full-time stable job. Uh I interviewed
with a few places. I had a few offers.
At the end of the day, the reason I came
back to Facebook was James Pierce. James
Pierce uh is a fantastic manager. He was
a director of engineering. He his claim
to fame is, you know, he was the manager
behind uh the open source program at
Facebook in the early days. He worked on
portal. He worked on so many amazing
things. Uh and I always looked up to
him. And so when it came time to find a
new role, I reached out to a few people
in my network, including James, and he
was like, "Yeah, I'll I'll take you.
Come work for me." So I inter, you know,
I interviewed I did a behavioral
interview cuz I boomeranged. Uh and they
were like, "Yeah, you're still you're
still not crazy. You can come back." Uh
got a few other offers, but like at the
end of the day, it was really the draw
of working with, you know, a few people
I really knew and respected. And then I
understand that you went to Clubhouse
after before.
>> Yeah.
>> Yeah. After, you know, so this is the
crazy thing. I I came back to to
Facebook in the summer of 2020. Uh spent
about seven months working on data
infrastructure
uh kind of related to the stuff I had
done before. And then a buddy of mine
just put me in touch with one of the
co-founders of Clubhouse. And now, you
know, if you remember, Clubhouse is the
like went crazy viral uh and crazy
growth in like late uh 2020, early 2021.
And I remember, you know, talking to
them at first, not seriously, because I
was like, I've just been back at
Facebook for seven months. I can leave
now. Uh but I talked to like the two
founders and I was like, "Oh, this is
exciting. Oh my god, Zuck is on
Clubhouse and like there's all of those
people." Like it was having a moment. uh
it was you know all the talk and and so
yeah I decided to join Clubhouse you
know when I joined Clubhouse the company
was like maybe 10 11 people insane
amount of hype around it a lot of users
and yeah it was a very interesting year
I spent there
>> you have any interesting insights or
stories that you'd like to share
>> I joined the company to help with the
data stack uh there was one person
working on data when I joined uh Kenny
Dika uh who was starting to put together
the analytic stack. Uh there was no
machine learning at Clubhouse. There was
no feed ranking or at least not machine
learned feed ranking. Clubhouse was like
spamming people with notifications. And
so a lot of like the work I did in the
early days was just building a lot of
those systems. Uh you know, like I said,
built AB testing for Instagram, built AB
testing for Clubhouse, uh cuz we wanted
to be able to measure the stuff we were
building. introduced some machine
learning to Clubhouse to filter out the
notifications we were sending because it
was very spammy.
>> What was the internal culture like?
>> The the culture was just very hands-on.
Uh a lot of people were very very eager,
extremely talented pool of engineers.
Clubhouse was like this interesting mix
where I think you know a large fraction
of the company was either former
Coinbase or former Facebook pretty much.
Yeah. a lot of like very independent
uh self-driven hungry engineers who just
wanted to build a really really cool
authentic social network.
>> So after Clubhouse, you went back to
Meta for a second boomerang.
>> For a second boomerang, I guess I had
like unfinished business at Meta. No,
you know, when I decided to leave
Clubhouse, I actually did a very
thorough job search. I ended up talking
to a lot of companies. I had an offer
from Apple that I really considered. The
reason I decided to go to Meta was
twofold. One, a manager, Vincent Hardy,
who had been my manager in the past,
whom I wanted to work with again.
Vincent at the time was the manager, the
engineering director behind Rayban
Stories.
Uh Rayban Stories is this partnership,
you know, the glasses between Meta and
uh Rayban. And I was like, I've never
worked on a product. I've never worked
on hardware. I have this connection who
is working on that and he's willing to
take a chance on me. I kind of want to
see what that pivot would look like
being, you know, not being the data guy
anymore, but kind of like working on
something else. Yeah, that was one thing
I wanted to know, which was you were
entrusted with this Uber TL role working
on in a very different domain than than
your past experience. And so it sounds
like the the key that got you that role
was that you uh came through referral
through someone a trusted past manager.
No, not entirely. So I I was not
interested with like any Uber TL role
from the get-go. You know, I came back
to the company as an IC7. Uh Rayan
stories had been released in September
of 2021. And after after launch, uh
there were quality issues, there were
growth issues. And so when I came in,
what I was asked to do was like, hey,
can you like look at our growth story?
Like you you know about data. Can you
look at like the data stuff a little
bit? Make sure like you know we're we're
dotting our eyes and crossing our tees.
And so I spent about eight months a year
uh working with fantastic leaders and
engineers and data people on Rayban
stories to understand like where were
things breaking uh where did we need to
invest more where do we need to measure
more and and that's how I built the
trust with that organization. So I spent
about a year doing that and then there
was a reorg at the end of 2022.
We merged a bunch of organizations
together and people started getting
different roles and you know we moved
people around and I told my manager at
the time hey you know it's been fun to
do this but the reason I joined smart
classes in the first place was I wanted
to work on smart classes I didn't want
to be the data guy anymore there's this
project uh I would really really like to
work on that I know I don't have
experience in hardware and product but
like you've seen you know my track
record of the last year I've developed
this like product sense can I go help
with that and he was like yeah you can
you move on to that project and work on
that. There was another engineer who was
actually the Uber TL and the STTO for
that entire program. And so I spent the
next couple of years essentially like
working on that and just kind of like
gaining more scope over time. And I
ended up, you know, kind of like
supervising all experiences across this
specific hardware line. I don't go into
details because the product is not yet
released, but my job was to make sure
like all of the experiences, the user
experiences uh on this specific device
were good. And so that meant working
with a lot of different teams across
smart glasses and eventually uh what
became wearables towards the end to make
sure like we were shipping the right set
of user experiences. Were there any
growing pains in switching into this new
domain?
>> I think there were a lot of growing
pains in the organization as the
organization was growing and maturing.
Uh and so naturally those kind of like
rippled onto me in the early days. I
struggled a lot with working or the the
cadence around working with hardware.
you know, I started working in 2022 on
something that will be released at some
point is currently not released. And so
this like extremely long lead time and
validation and like you know putting
things in the hand of users uh was was
kind of missing. But once I got to a
point where at least there was like
internal fish fooding and dog fooding
within within the company uh and we
started getting like some feedback and
some signal uh that made things a little
easier. Do you have any advice on how to
ramp up successfully in like a
completely different domain?
>> I think it's the same thing as like
ramping up at a new company uh or a
different flavor of it. I I use the, you
know, the boss strategy of doing the
social network exploration thing first.
Uh talk to people, ask them who I should
be talking to. Don't be afraid to ask
dumb questions. Like you're the noob on
the team. Like everyone knows that you
don't know anything. Uh, I'd rather ask
a really silly question now rather than
six months from now, uh, not know what
we're talking about. And try and get
your hands dirty. It's a thing I've
always tried to do. Check out the code.
Even if you're not going to like work on
like I never officially worked on
firmware, right? Uh, I did check out the
code and I did make a few tweaks just to
like get a feel for it, get an
understanding of it. Uh, and then kind
of like map things out this way. And
then I'd say the last thing I'd say is
pick a hard problem to solve. I learn a
lot by doing. Uh and so you know this
might not translate to other people but
like I learn by doing. So I pick a hard
problem to solve where I have kind of
like an idea of how to solve the thing
and then I can fill in the blanks as I
go and that's where I learned
>> on this team. This is where you got your
IC8 promo or your principal engineer
promo. What I'm curious what's the story
behind that promotion? what is the scope
that actually got you promoted?
>> Well, so in this case, I was eventually
responsible, like I said, for like all
experiences on a device. Uh, and so I
was working across multiple orgs, you
know, dozens of teams. I think at some
point like the the set of PMs I was
interacting with was probably like 35 or
so PMs. Uh, and like you know, however
many engineering teams uh are working
with that. Uh my job at that point
became a lot of like coordination and
just like overall architecture and my
responsibility was making sure that we
were delivering on our milestones from
an experiences perspective. The the
reason I say experiences and not the
whole device by the way is that the way
we were organized is there were teams
working on the OS layer. Uh and you know
I would like work a little bit with them
and communicate requirements and like
poke holes into their story. uh but
there were partners. I was not
responsible for like that part of the
stack. My responsibility was very
specifically on the experiences we were
shipping. So if you think about say
Rayban Meta for example, uh which is a
product that's in market, the
experiences on that would be all of the
AI on the device, all of the music
listening, the photo capture, and then
all of the companion app stuff. So you
can imagine something like that for
another device. Uh so that was scope.
Uh, I can go into a little bit of
details on like how I actually got the
promo because that one was a little bit
more work. Like if I think about like my
entire, you know, set of promotions from
IC5 to IC8, IC5, I had no idea that
promo was a thing. Uh, it was kind of
like a surprise. IC6, I had to like talk
to my manager uh and be like, "Okay, do
you think we can put me up for promo?"
Uh, and my manager was like, "Yeah,
okay. Yeah, I think you're ready. And it
went through. Uh IC7, it took a couple
of cycles where we like to like do a few
revs. IC8,
uh I went to my manager and my manager
at the time had never done an ICA promo
and we're like, "Okay, so how do we do
this?" Uh you know, we partnered on
writing the promo packet together. I
wrote like a substantial amount of the
promo packet obviously with his help. uh
and then you know building consensus
within the organization uh going to like
multiple VPs uh early on and be like you
know this is the work that I've been
doing you see the ICA scope here would
you be supportive of the promotion and
like building that consensus and seeking
that mentorship in some cases you know
there was a D2 in the organization who I
knew would be absolutely critical in me
getting this promotion and so I went to
him and I was like you carry a lot of
weight in this organization. I'd love to
understand how I can make it to that
level. Would you mind just having like
a, you know, monthly conversation with
me, just checking in and helping me
course correct? And so 6 months later
when, you know, I went up for promo, uh,
he was supportive cuz like he had been
involved in the process the whole time.
>> So identifying who the champions are is
even more important for the highest
level promotions and working with them
to kind of understand what your gaps
are. So that when it comes time for that
discussion, it's just a matter of
logistics that everyone is already
aligned prior to that room.
>> Yes. Now to be clear, uh I don't want to
make it sound like getting promoted is
just a sourceful game. Like you need to
have the underlying work, too, but you
need to have both of those things. you
need to have like the impact in the
underlying work but then it is also way
easier at least in my experience to like
build the consensus ahead of time so
that when you go to a you know
performance calibration session you
don't have to you don't have a debate in
the room uh and so for my IC promo it
took two cycles like the first one we
started socializing my manager even
didn't even put me up for promo
officially in in that cycle he just
talked to people around and be you know,
just feeling the water. And then in the
following half, people had that context
that like, oh, we're having this
conversation. This is going to happen
eventually. Uh, let's see what's
missing, what we can do this half. Uh,
>> and then obviously then, you know, with
the amount of work I did in that half
and the impact I had and that support
and mentorship, that's how I ended up
getting it. when it comes to the scope
and the role that got you promoted, it
is it's a role that it it requires
permission from from those around you to
have that role. You know, there's
there's only one Uber tech lead on I
mean, you know, relatively there's one
of that role available. It's not like
you kind of like your Bento story, you
created a role without permission from
others and you kind of built it up into
something. when it comes to that first
type where there's there's a limited
role and there's probably other people
who would like to have that role, do you
have any advice on how to secure that
that scope for yourself or, you know, go
go towards that if that's something
you're interested in? So, funnily
enough, that's not exactly the case
because in this case there there was an
Uber TL for this entire program and he's
a fantastic engineer Jensen Yu. Uh I
just identified that there was a lot of
work on experiences specifically on the
experiences side working with product
and design that I could help with where
you know he could focus on like the
broader program and I could just like
narrowly tackle that area. And so, you
know, over time, he and I built this
trust where I just started focusing on
that and I started taking that off his
plate. He didn't have to worry too much
about it. Instead of having to
coordinate with like 10 or 12 different
engineering teams on experiences
specifically, he could just go through
me. Uh the system stuff, everything else
he would do himself, but I ran a very
tight chip on experiences and so I made
his life easier. Uh and so in a way, I
kind of like took that role upon myself.
uh like there isn't really like an Uber
TL for experiences on each product line.
I just kind of like, you know, carved
that out uh for myself within that
specific program. Uh now, at some point,
you know, I worked with my leadership.
Uh and I was like, hey, I've been doing
this thing uh and people are asking like
why is Adrian doing that? Do you mind if
we just say that like I'm the TL and
experiences? That would make my life
easier. But it became uh a post hawk
thing you know once I was already doing
the work and I had done the work for
about a year at that point I just asked
to be blessed with like a little label
so that I could explain who I was in a
sentence as opposed to I'm just this
engineer who's like touching all of the
experiences. Another thing I really want
to make clear here is that you know I've
I've heard a lot of engineers talking
about scope as in like stealing scope
from other people. That is the wrong way
to think about it. You know, taking
something off someone's plate doesn't
mean that you're stealing from them. Or
it is if you're not talking to them
about it. So again, I and and this is a
constant across everything I've been
talking about. Overcommunicate. I went
to that engineer. I was like, "Hey, I am
very excited about this space. Do you
mind if I like help with this?" And he's
like, "Yeah, sure. I you know, I'm
swamped. If you want to take that on,
take it on." And then you know I come
back a few weeks later and say hey
there's this other kind of like related
thing uh is it okay if I talk to them?
He's like yeah sure knock yourself out
and like you know in the process then he
can go and like explore other things uh
and broaden his own scope.
>> Yeah in my mind it's it's a win-win for
for him because I mean I imagine you
helped him scale himself so he can you
know chase some other scope. Maybe he's
going for IC9 or something like that and
he has evidence that he grew someone to
IC8 or helped. I don't know if that was
the case in this this example, but
oftent times TLS are gracious to give
scope so that they can move on to bigger
things and help you grow into their
role. And similarly, I've done that, you
know, with like more junior engineers
where I had to actually fight with more
junior engineers and tell them, hey, can
you can you actually take that and like
just own it? uh like it's going to be
good for you. I also would love to like
be able to delegate that to someone. So
coming to the end of your career story,
I I wanted to do some reflecting across
some of the things that that I saw. One
thing I wanted to ask was you have a
unique skill set that is very software
engineering heavy and also very data
heavy from your past experience. And I'm
curious what unique career experiences
were only possible through that lens.
>> I think all of them. Uh I I think I've
always tried to be a well-rounded
engineer. And you know in addition to
software engineering and like data, I
think I've always tried to like develop
a strong product sense and a strong
design sense. At Facebook, we have like
those uh archetypes once you reach uh
senior staff and principal. And I've
always been a product hybrid. Uh and to
me, like this like well-roundedness is
where I can add value. Uh being able to
both, you know, have like a deep product
conversation with product management
leaders and the next day go down and
like debug some like firmware code. uh
like being a well-rounded person I think
is one of the things that uh I've always
taken pride in. Uh Robert Heinline has
this quote uh where he says like a
competent man should be able to like do
all of those things uh you know write a
sonnet die calently and whatnot and he
finishes and says specialization is for
insects. Uh and it's it's one of the
things that like I've always taken to
heart. I I love learning and I want to
try and be good at a lot of different
things. Uh and then you know bring this
like panel of things to the table. And
so when I was working uh in wearables
you know I would like build little
prototypes uh you know like design my
own little circuit boards and like hack
things together like obviously not
production ready. I'm not a hardware
engineer, but like having the ability to
do that type of stuff means that you can
start a conversation with people. You
can go and, you know, talk to a product
lead and be like, "Hey, I have this
idea. Here's a thing you can play with."
One thing you said, and this is evident
to me throughout your career. You said
something that, you know, your career is
a series of bumping into the right
people or you you you mentioned a quote
like that. And throughout each leg of
your story, there there tends to be
someone who either brought you along or
was instrumental in one of the projects
that got you promoted. I'm curious, do
you have any tips on how to I guess
maximize your luck when it comes to
people opportunity?
>> Oh, so many thoughts. Uh the first one
is, you know, like I I've been talking a
lot about myself for the last like hour
now. None of the stuff I've done would
have been possible if I was working in a
vacuum. like everything I've done has
been, you know, working on a team,
convincing people, getting people to,
you know, go in bad for me. Like some
younger software engineers, I had rough
edges when I was earlier on in my
career. I had like very strong opinions
about things and that didn't always work
out in my favor. And and so I learned
very quickly that, you know, we're all
in this to succeed. And the best way to
succeed is to help others succeed. Not
to want anything in return, but just,
you know, fostering success around you,
right? A rising tide lifts all boats.
And that's the thing that I've been
trying to do in my career probably for
the last decade or so. You know, the
first like two, three years of my
career, I was maybe a little selfish.
And then I started realizing, hey, we
can all succeed together. And so, when
you build that trust, and you know, I'm
not saying I'm going to be friends with
all of my co-workers. When you have
relations, relationships of trust and
respect with people, that is a really
good way of making sure like eventually
if you have a need, that person is going
to be there for you. Like you don't do
that in order for them to be there for
you. You just you are a good person. You
are a trustworthy person. You build
trust and then you will reap the
benefits of being a good person
eventually. That's one thing. Two, don't
be afraid to ask. Every career change
I've made, I have never applied for any
job on a website. I have always reached
out to someone I know. Once you build
this relationship of trust with people
and you, you know, you're comfortable
asking them and be like, "Hey, there's
no pressure. You can say no if you don't
want to, but would you mind just giving
me like doing me a little favor?" So,
don't be a dick essentially. Uh, you
know, build trustworthy relationship
with people. Don't be afraid to ask, but
also don't be afraid to hear no or not
hear back from people. Uh people are
busy. That's fine. The way you maximize
your luck is you maximize I was reading
something the other day about like the
surface area for luck. Take more shots.
The more shots you take, the more likely
you are for one to land. And then the
last question I'd like to ask you is um
if you could go back to yourself when
you just graduated college in France and
give yourself some advice knowing what
you know today, what would you say? Be a
good person. Invest in things that are
fun. Invest in your relationship with
your co-workers. Uh it doesn't it
doesn't really matter at the end of the
day who gets the credit. Everyone is
going to get credit for something. I
think early on in my career I was very
credit driven. Be patient. You know, I I
think it there were a few times in my
career where I was pushing for a promo
or when I wasn't ready. Uh like my IC7,
like I said, took like a a couple of
halves to go through and stay curious
and mostly just like enjoy it. Uh you're
going to have an amazing adventure.
Awesome. Well, thanks so much for
sharing your career story with us,
Adrian. And now, if you want to um you
know, share with the audience where
people could find you, maybe they can go
and I'll put it in the show notes.
>> Sure. I at this point I'm mostly just
active on LinkedIn so we can put my
LinkedIn in there. Uh and then yeah, no
plugs. I hope that the audience will get
something out of this.
>> Awesome. Thanks so much for sharing this
with the community. Thank you so much
for having me, Ryan.
>> Thanks for listening to the podcast. I
don't sell anything or do sponsorships,
but if you want to help out with the
podcast, you can support by engaging
with the content on YouTube or on
Spotify. If you want to drop a review,
that'll be super helpful. And if there's
any guests that you want to bring on to,
please let me know. I feel like sourcing
very senior IC's, there's no wellstudied
list out there on Google that I can just
search this up. So, if there's someone
in your org or at your company who you
really look up to and you want to hear
their career story, let me know and I'll
reach out to